87. Stuttering. Stuttering, also called stammering, is a communication disorder.
People who stutter have a very difficult time speaking. When they try to talk, they seem
to get stuck on words or sounds. They may repeat the beginning sound of a word many
times as in, my n-n-name is. Or they may make the same sound for a long time before they
are able to say the word as in, my n-n-name is. They may also have trouble making any
sound at all when they talk. Stuttering is still a mysterious problem. It affects more
boys than girls. It usually becomes obvious at a young age soon after a child starts talking.
One cause of stuttering seems to be genetic. However, not all stutterers have the stuttering
gene. It may also be caused by trauma early in life or other factors in a child's development.
Most children outgrow stuttering, but for some people, the problem continues into adulthood.
Stuttering is not a consistent problem. It gets better or worse depending on the situation.
Singing often reduces stuttering, while public speaking or even talking on the phone can
make it much worse. Stuttering causes a lot of emotional stress.
Stutterers may feel tense and anxious in social situations or ashamed of the way they speak.
This causes some stutterers to stay away from other people, which can lead to loneliness
and depression. Now people are accepting stuttering more, and stutterers are becoming less ashamed.
There are many famous people who have stuttered. King George VI of England, for example, and
Lewis Carroll, who wrote Alice in Wonderland. Even Julia Roberts stuttered at one point.
There's even a Facebook page for stutterers to join. Sounding different shouldn't mean
you can't communicate.